Guide to the Collection of Geraldine Farrar Correspondence and Other Material
Yale University Music Library
Collection of Geraldine Farrar correspondence and other material
1927-1967
MSS 101
Yale University Music Library
1
3 boxes
This collection includes soprano Geraldine Farrar's handwritten correspondence, primarily to Charles Mills and William H. Seltsam; a large scrapbook by Charles Mills of Farrar clippings, photographs, and Christmas cards; photographs of Farrar; and miscellaneous programs, promotional material, and articles.
Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Sketch of Geraldine Farrar
Soprano Geraldine Farrar was born in Melrose, Massachusetts, 28 February 1882. Her father, Sidney Farrar, was a baseball player.
Farrar studied in Boston, New York City, and Paris. Her teachers included Francesco Graziani, J. H. Long, and Emma Thursby. Farrar débuted at the Königliches Opernhaus, Berlin, as Marguerite in Gounod's Faust, 15 October 1901. Shortly after, she became a pupil of Lilli Lehmann, and sang Zerlina in Mozart's Don Giovanniin Salzburg alongside Lehmann as Donna Anna. Farrar also performed at the Opéra de Monte Carlo in 1904, singing Mimi in Puccini's La Bohèmeand Gilda in Verdi's Rigoletto, on several occasions alongside tenor Enrico Caruso.
After five years in Berlin, Farrar joined the Metropolitan Opera in New York City, where, in 1906, she first appeared as Juliette Gounod's Roméo et Juliette. She quickly became one of the leading stars of the company. In 1907 she also sang in the Metropolitan Opera's first production of Puccini's Madama Butterfly. Farrar created the title role in Amicaby Mascagni (Monte Carlo, 1905), Goose Girl in Humperdink's Königskinder(New York City, 1910), and the title role in Puccini's Suor Angelica(New York City, 1918).
Farrar was engaged ina seven-year love affair with the Italian conductor Arturo Toscanini. In 1915 her ultimatum to him, that he leave his wife and children and marry her, resulted in Toscanini's abrupt resignation as principal conductor of the Metropolitan Opera. Farrar then married cinema actor Lou Tellegen on 8 February 1916 and divorced in 1923.
Farrar remained at the Metropolitan until 1922, when she made her farewell performance in Leoncavallo's Zazàon 22 April. She sang nearly 500 times with the Metropolitan Opera and made many recordings. Later Farrar appeared in a number of films and in 1960 was awarded two stars on the Hollywood Walk of Fame, in the music and film categories. Farrar also published an autobiography on 1938 entitled Such Sweet Compulsion.
Farrar died of a heart attack in Ridgefield, Connecticut, on 11 March 1967 (age 85). She was buried in Kensico Cemetery in Valhalla, New York. She had no children.
Scope and Contents
The material within this collection, including correspondence, photographs, promotional clippings, and articles, was primarily generated after Geraldine Farrar stopped singing operatic roles on stage. The bulk of the correspondence consists of handwrittenand typed letters from Farrar to Charles Mills (1957 Nov 1 –1967 Mar 15), and an extensive collection of similar letters between Farrar and William H. Seltsam (1930 Jun 25 –1966 Jul 22). The letters to Charles Mill concern normal cordial matters and occasionally mention performances Farrar saw and listened to, such as Puccini's Tosca. The Mills letters also mention and describe performances Farrar worked with, befriended, or admired, including Mattia Battistini, Claudia Muzio, Emma Calvé, Nellie Melba,and her former teacher and colleague, Lilli Lehmann. The letters between Farrar and Seltsam primarily concern Farrar's many recordings. Paper materials include one leather-bound book from Farrar to Marguerite Mills for her birthday in 1964, which contains a letter and a pencil sketch of an unknown face (perhaps Farrar or Mrs. Mills); other handwritten and typed letters, including those to Mr. Jerrold N. Moore, Mr. Howell, and Mr. Night; two ink sketches with a repertoire or program listing; a copy of Opera Newswith an article on Farrar's death; and several articles about Farrar and the various roles she performed on stage. The collection also includes photographs, both of Farrar in portraits and Farrar in costume for various roles.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, and II. Photographs, articles, and ephemera.
Correspondence; Sopranos (singers); Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967
- Correspondence, 1930-1967; Series I
  - Jerold N. Moore, Mr. Howell, and Mr. Knight, 1951–1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles Mills, 1956 December 9–1966 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Envelopes.
  - Charles Mills, 1957 January 6–1960 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charles Mills, 1957 November 1–1967 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sylvia Blein on behalf of Farrar to Charles Mills.
  - Charles Mills, 1960 February 13–1962 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Charles Mills, 1963 February 23–1966 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marguerite Mills, 1959 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Commemorative birthday letter with drawing.
  - William H. Seltsam, 1930 May 25–1931 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - William H. Seltsam, 1932–1934 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - William H. Seltsam, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - William H. Seltsam, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - William H. Seltsam, 1937–1939 November 24 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - William H. Seltsam, 1940 April–1953 December 3 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - William H. Seltsam, 1954 March 8–1959 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Willian H. Seltsam, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Willian H. Seltsam; Miss Gardoni, 1960–1966 July 22 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Photographs, articles, and ephemera, 1927-1967; Series II
  - Photographs of Geraldine Farrar, 1927–1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Programs, articles, and clippings, 1927–1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Painting print and portrait photograph, circa 1929 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Oversize.
  - Opera News: article on Geralldine Farrar's death, 1967 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook of Geraldine Farrar by Charles Mills, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Invitation to hospital benefit, two pen and ink sketches, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)